Guide to the Letters to Herbert Van Thal
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Letters to Herbert Van Thal
1921-1980
GEN MSS 464
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.6
(2 boxes)
Letters to Herbert Van Thal from various writers, critics, readers, and actors, including James Agate, Alan Dent, Adrian Conan Doyle, Roger Fulford, Elspeth Huxley, Noel Langley, James Pope-Hennessey, Leonard Russell and Paul Scott. Many letters concern projects proposed by Van Thal, such as memoirs by famous persons, or are in response to queries placed by Van Thal soliciting information or leads for compilations of letters he was preparing. Other letters concern his work as a writers' agent.
Van Thal, Herbert, 1904-1983
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Bertram Rota on the George Henry Nettleton Fund, 1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
HERBERT VAN THAL (1904-1983)
Herbert Van Thal's career in literary matters was varied and successful, Beginning as a bookseller's assistant, he worked for publishers before establishing his own firm, Home and Van Thal. In 1937, he edited the collection The Royal Letter Book, beginning a series of anthologies and reprints of classics that would bear his name. In the 1960s and 1970s, he earned a niche of renown for his anthologies of horror stories. Along the way, he acted as literary agent for a number of writers and wrote original works, such as Eliza Lynn Linton: The Girl of the Period. More information can be found in his autobiography, The Tops of the Mulberry Trees.
Scope and Contents
The letters to Herbert Van Thal consist of items from various writers, critics, readers, and actors, including James Agate, Alan Dent, Adrian Conan Doyle, Roger Fulford, Elspeth Huxley, Noel Langley, James Pope-Hennessey, Leonard Russell and Paul Scott. Many letters concern projects proposed by Van Thal, such as memoirs by famous persons, or are in response to queries placed by Van Thal soliciting information or leads for compilations of letters he was preparing. Other letters concern his work as a writers' agent.
Authors, English -- 20th Century; Literary agents -- Great Britain -- Archives; Authors; Literary agents; Agate, James, 1877-1947; Dent, Alan, 1905-1978; Doyle, Adrian Conan; Fulford, Roger, 1902-1983; Huxley, Elspeth, 1907-1997; Langley, Noel, 1911-1980; Pope-Hennessy, James; Russell, Leonard, 1906-; Scott, Paul, 1920-1978; Van Thal, Herbert, 1904-1983
- Box and folder list, 1964, n.d.
  - "A" general, 1964, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Acton, Harold, 1942 Dec 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Agate, James, 1926-47 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes letter from JA's sister, May (ca. 1947)
  - Alwyn, William, 1966-73 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ashbrook, William, 1961-64 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Atholl, Katharine, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "B" general, 1936-79 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Balcon, Michael, 1954 Sep 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Barry, Gerald, 1951 Jun 13 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bates, Ralph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Beaverbrook, Max Aitken, Baron [Lord Beaverbrook], 1956, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bellezza, Vincenzo, 1958 Mar 22 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bentley, Phyllis, 1948-70 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Berners, Gerald Hugh Tyrwhitt-Wilson, Baron [Lord Berners], 1942 Aug 8 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Blackwell, Basil, 1955 Oct 13 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bland, J. O. P., 1922 Mar 31 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Blount, Trevor, 1972 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bogarde, Dirk, 1976-77, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Boult, Adrian, 1949 Apr 28 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bowen, Marjorie, 1949-50 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Butler, R. A. B. [Butler of Saffron Walden, Richard Austen Butler, Baron], 1974 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "C" general, 1935-72 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Carter, John, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Cockerell, Sydney Carlyle, Sir, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Cohen, Harriet, 1934 Oct 20 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Collins, Vere H., 1952, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Coward, Thomas R., 1953 Feb 26 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Curran, Charles, 1947 Feb 21 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "D" general, 1949, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Denison, Michael, 1973 Oct 20 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Dent, Alan, 1935-73 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Dodge, David, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Doyle, Adrian Conan, 1947-48 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Dobree, Bonamy, 1933 Jul 22 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Downs, Brian, 1951 Jul 10 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Easson, Angus, 1973 Oct 20 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Elizabeth II, 1948 Jan 30 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    From a Lady in Waiting
  - Elizabeth, Queen [consort], 1948, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    From a secretary
  - Evans, Margiad, 1953 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - "F" general, 1952-74, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Fairfield, Letitia, 1974, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Flower, Desmond (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Foyle, Christina, 1965 Feb 2 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Includes letters from the Prime Minister's secretary in response to HVT's recommendation of CF for an Honour (1962, 1965)
  - Fulford, Roger, 1935-73, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - "G" general, 1943, 1947, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Gillet, Eric, 1974 Jan 26 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Gish, Lillian, 1946 Jul 26 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Gordon, John, 1961 Dec 22 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Gribble, George Dunning, 1925 Mar 3 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Grylls, R. Glynn, 1939 Aug 21 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Guinness, Alec, 1965 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Gwynn, Stephen, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - "H" general, 1921-75 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Haight, Gordon S., 1947 Jun 8 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Haley, William, 1965-66 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Harding, James, 1965-79, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Harling, Robert, 1954-59 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Heath, Edward, 1964 Jun 3 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Henrey, Robert, Mrs., 1950 Aug 27 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Hoeck, Mary C., 1965 Aug 27 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    Includes photographs of letters to Mary Hoeck from Jean Cocteau (ca. 1956-59)
  - Hoppe, A. J., 1941 Sep 5 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Hughes, David, 1950, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Hughes, Gervase, 1971 Sep 15 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Huxley, Elspeth, 1969-80 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    Includes letter from unidentified associate of EH (1969)
  - Israel, H. E., Mrs., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - "J" general, 1939, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - "Kemsley", 1944 Sep 25 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - King, Robin, 1960, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - [King], Francis, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Knoblock, Edward, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Kuneralp, Zeki, 1970, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - "L" general, 1949-76 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - [Laughton?], Charles, 1938, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Langley, Noel, 1959-60, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Lehmann, Beatrix, n.D. (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Leslie, Shane, 1959 Jun 13 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Lewis, W. S., 1959 Jul 20 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Lytton, Victor Alexander George Robert Bulwer-Lytton, Earl, 1939-47 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - "M" general, 1935-65 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Marceau, Félicien, 1956 Sep 1 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Maxwell, Henry, 1939, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 81)
    Includes copy of letter from HVT
  - Miller, Jonathan, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Mitford, Nancy, 1942 Mar 24 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Morley, Frank V., 1980 Jul 29 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Morshead, Owen, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Mortimer, Raymond, 1957 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Newman, Ernest, 1954 Dec 16 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Osborne, Eric, 1958-59, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - "P" general, 1965, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Painter, George, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Parish, James, 1948 Oct 21 (Box 1, Folder 91)
    Letter from a lawyer on behalf of JP
  - Parry, Edward Abbott, 1930 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Partridge, Eric, 1974, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Pritchett, V. S., 1944, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Philby, H. St. J. B., 1943 Jun 8 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Playfair, Nigel, 1926 Feb 17 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Pope-Hennessy, James, [1949?], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Pope-Hennessy, Una, Dame, 1947, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Powell, Dilys, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Price, Nancy, 1947 Oct 30 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Quigly, Isabel, 1958 May 23 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - "R" general, 1941-70 (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Rank, J. Arthur, 1943-44 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Rawlings, Margaret, 1941 Mar 1 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Rolph, C. H., 1965 Aug 1 (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - Russell, Leonard, 1954-55 (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - "S" general, 1931-72 (Box 2, Folder 107)
    Includes copies of letters from HVT
  - St. John-Stevas, Norman, 1973 Dec (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - Sansom, William, 1956-73 (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - Scott, Paul, 1975, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 110)
  - Selms, F. M., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - Shawe-Taylor, Desmond, 1962 Nov 21 (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - Simpson, Helen, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - Smiles, Aileen, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - Speaight, Robert, 1954, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 115)
  - Speilmann, M. H., 1924 Jan 31 (Box 2, Folder 116)
  - Stonier, G. W., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 117)
  - Stern, G. B., 1935, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 118)
  - Stopes, Marie, 1933 May 12 (Box 2, Folder 119)
  - Stuart, Dorothy Margaret, 1951 Sep 21 (Box 2, Folder 120)
  - Swallow, Alan, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 121)
  - Swanwick, Betty, 1959 Jan 31 (Box 2, Folder 122)
  - "T" general, 1953-76, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 123)
  - Thurston, Herbert, 1935 May (Box 2, Folder 124)
  - Tweedsmuir, Susan, 1947 Jul (Box 2, Folder 125)
  - Unwin, Stanley, 1960 Jun 10 (Box 2, Folder 126)
  - Vaughan, Herbert M., 1939 Aug 13 (Box 2, Folder 127)
  - "W" general, 1931-73 (Box 2, Folder 128)
  - Wedgwood, C. V. (Cicely Veronica), 1949, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 129)
  - Williams, George Charles, 1936 Feb 25 (Box 2, Folder 130)
  - Wilson, Mary, 1963 Feb 19 (Box 2, Folder 131)
  - Unidentified, 1947-76 (Box 2, Folder 132)